<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="pretvorba.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE podaci SYSTEM "gramatika.dtd">

<podaci>
    <glumac glumacId="1" nacionalnost="US" glumacSpol="M" wikiPageTitle="Jeff Goldblum" brojDjece="2">
        <ime>Jeff</ime>
        <prezime>Goldblum</prezime>
        <datum_rodjenja>October 22, 1952</datum_rodjenja>
        <partner statusVeze="Rastavljeni">
            <partnerIme>Patricia</partnerIme>
            <partnerPrezime>Gaul</partnerPrezime>
        </partner>
        <partner statusVeze="Rastavljeni">
            <partnerIme>Geena</partnerIme>
            <partnerPrezime>Davis</partnerPrezime>
        </partner>
        <partner statusVeze="Oženjeni">
            <partnerIme>Emilie</partnerIme>
            <partnerPrezime>Livingston</partnerPrezime>
        </partner>
        <zanimanje imeZanimanja="Glumac"/>
        <biografija>
            Jeffrey Lynn Goldblum (born October 22, 1952) is an American actor and musician.
            He has starred in some of the highest-grossing films of his era,
            Jurassic Park (1993) and Independence Day (1996), as well as their respective sequels,
            The Lost World: Jurassic Park (1997) and Jurassic World: Fallen Kingdom (2018),
            and Independence Day: Resurgence (2016).
            Goldblum starred in films including Invasion of the Body Snatchers (1978),
            The Big Chill (1983), and Into the Night (1985)
            before coming to the attention of wider audiences
            in David Cronenberg's The Fly (1986) which earned him a Saturn Award for Best Actor.
            His other films include The Adventures of Buckaroo Banzai Across the 8th Dimension (1984),
            The Tall Guy (1989), Deep Cover (1992), Powder (1995),
            The Prince of Egypt (1998), Cats &amp; Dogs (2001), Igby Goes Down (2002),
            The Life Aquatic with Steve Zissou (2004), Adam Resurrected (2008),
            Le Week-End (2013), The Grand Budapest Hotel (2014), and Thor: Ragnarok (2017).
            He also starred in several TV series including the eighth and ninth seasons of
            Law &amp; Order: Criminal Intent as Zack Nichols. For directing the short film Little Surprises,
            he was nominated for the Academy Award for Best Live Action Short Film.
        </biografija>
        <filmografija>Death Wish, Nashville, Annie Hall, The Fly, Jurassic Park, Independence Day, Independence Day 2
        </filmografija>
        <rezidencija>Los Angeles, California, U.S.</rezidencija>
        <rezidencija>New York, New York, U.S.</rezidencija>
    </glumac>


    <glumac glumacId="2" nacionalnost="US" glumacSpol="M" wikiPageTitle="Marlon Brando" brojDjece="11">
        <ime>Marlon</ime>
        <prezime>Brando</prezime>
        <datum_rodjenja>April 3, 1924</datum_rodjenja>
        <datum_smrti>July 1, 2004</datum_smrti>
        <visina>175 cm</visina>
        <partner statusVeze="Rastavljeni">
            <partnerIme>Anna</partnerIme>
            <partnerPrezime>Kashfi</partnerPrezime>
        </partner>
        <partner statusVeze="Rastavljeni">
            <partnerIme>Movita</partnerIme>
            <partnerPrezime>Castaneda</partnerPrezime>
        </partner>
        <partner statusVeze="Rastavljeni">
            <partnerIme>Tarita</partnerIme>
            <partnerPrezime>Teriipaia</partnerPrezime>
        </partner>
        <zanimanje imeZanimanja="Glumac"/>
        <zanimanje imeZanimanja="Redatelj"/>
        <biografija>
            Marlon Brando Jr. (April 3, 1924 – July 1, 2004) was an American actor and film director.
            With a career spanning 60 years,
            he is well-regarded for his cultural influence on 20th-century film.
            Brando's Academy Award-winning performances include that of Terry Malloy in On the Waterfront (1954)
            and Don Vito Corleone in The Godfather (1972). Brando was an activist for many causes,
            notably the civil rights movement and various Native American movements.
            He is credited with helping to popularize the Stanislavski system of acting,
            having studied with Stella Adler in the 1940s.
            He is often regarded as one of the first actors to bring Method Acting to mainstream audiences.
            He initially gained acclaim and an Academy Award nomination for reprising the role of Stanley Kowalski
            in the 1951 film adaptation of Tennessee Williams' play A Streetcar Named Desire,
            a role that he originated successfully on Broadway.
            He received further praise for his performance as Terry Malloy in On the Waterfront,
            and his portrayal of the rebellious motorcycle gang leader Johnny Strabler
            in The Wild One proved to be a lasting image in popular culture.
            Brando received Academy Award nominations for playing Emiliano Zapata in Viva Zapata!;
            Mark Antony in Joseph L. Mankiewicz's 1953 film adaptation of Shakespeare's Julius Caesar;
            and Air Force Major Lloyd Gruver in Sayonara (1957),
            an adaptation of James Michener's 1954 novel.
            Brando was included in a list of Top Ten Money Making Stars three times in the 1950s,
            coming in at number 10 in 1954, number 6 in 1955, and number 4 in 1958.
            The 1960s saw Brando's career take a downturn.
            He directed and starred in the cult western film One-Eyed Jacks,
            a critical and commercial flop, after which he delivered a series of box-office failures,
            beginning with the 1962 film adaptation of the novel Mutiny on the Bounty.
            After 10 years, during which he did not appear in a successful film,
            he won his second Academy Award for playing Vito Corleone in Francis Ford Coppola's The Godfather,
            a role critics consider among his greatest.
            The Godfather was then one of the most commercially successful films of all time.
            With that and his Oscar-nominated performance in Last Tango in Paris,
            Brando re-established himself in the ranks of top box-office stars,
            placing sixth and tenth in the Money Making Stars poll in 1972 and 1973,
            respectively. Brando took a four-year hiatus before appearing in The Missouri Breaks (1976).
            After this, he was content with being a highly paid character actor in cameo roles,
            such as in Superman (1978) and The Formula (1980), before taking a nine-year break from motion pictures.
            According to the Guinness Book of World Records,
            Brando was paid a record $3.7 million ($15 million in inflation-adjusted dollars)
            and 11.75% of the gross profits for 13 days' work on Superman.
            He finished out the 1970s with his controversial performance as Colonel Kurtz in another Coppola film,
            Apocalypse Now, a box-office hit for which he was highly paid and which helped
            finance his career layoff during the 1980s.
            Brando was ranked by the American Film Institute as the fourth-greatest movie star among male movie stars
            whose screen debuts occurred in or before 1950. He was one of six professional actors,
            along with Charlie Chaplin, U.S. President Ronald Reagan, Lucille Ball,
            Frank Sinatra, and Marilyn Monroe,
            named in 1999 by Time magazine as one of its 100 Most Important People of the Century.[7]
        </biografija>
        <filmografija>Godfahter, Last Tango in Paris, Apocalypse Now, Superman, On the Waterfront</filmografija>
    </glumac>


    <glumac glumacId="3" nacionalnost="US" glumacSpol="M" wikiPageTitle="Tom Hanks" brojDjece="4">
        <ime>Tom</ime>
        <prezime>Hanks</prezime>
        <datum_rodjenja>July 9, 1956</datum_rodjenja>
        <partner statusVeze="Rastavljeni">
            <partnerIme>Samantha</partnerIme>
            <partnerPrezime>Lewes</partnerPrezime>
        </partner>
        <partner statusVeze="Oženjeni">
            <partnerIme>Rita</partnerIme>
            <partnerPrezime>Wilson</partnerPrezime>
        </partner>
        <zanimanje imeZanimanja="Glumac"/>
        <zanimanje imeZanimanja="Redatelj"/>
        <biografija>
            Thomas Jeffrey Hanks (born July 9, 1956) is an American actor and filmmaker.
            Hanks is known for his comedic and dramatic roles in such films as Splash (1984),
            Big (1988), Turner &amp; Hooch (1989),
            A League of Their Own (1992),
            Sleepless in Seattle (1993), Apollo 13 (1995),
            You've Got Mail (1998), The Green Mile (1999), Cast Away (2000),
            Road to Perdition (2002), Cloud Atlas (2012), Captain Phillips (2013),
            Saving Mr. Banks (2013), and Sully (2016).
            He has also starred in the Robert Langdon film series,
            and voices Sheriff Woody in the Toy Story film series.
            He is one of the most popular and recognizable film stars worldwide,
            and is widely regarded as an American cultural icon.
            Hanks has collaborated with film director Steven Spielberg on five films to date:
            Saving Private Ryan (1998), Catch Me If You Can (2002), The Terminal (2004), Bridge of Spies (2015),
            and The Post (2017), as well as the 2001 miniseries Band of Brothers,
            which launched Hanks as a successful director, producer, and screenwriter. In 2010,
            Spielberg and Hanks were executive producers on the HBO miniseries The Pacific.
            Hanks' films have grossed more than $4.6 billion at U.S.
            and Canadian box offices and more than $9.2 billion worldwide,
            making him the fourth highest-grossing actor in North America.
            Hanks has been nominated for numerous awards during his career.
            He won a Golden Globe Award and an Academy Award for Best Actor for his role in Philadelphia (1993),
            as well as a Golden Globe, an Academy Award, a Screen Actors Guild Award,
            and a People's Choice Award for Best Actor for Forrest Gump (1994).
            In 1995, Hanks became one of only two actors who won the Academy Award for Best Actor in consecutive years,
            with Spencer Tracy being the other. In 2004,
            he received the Stanley Kubrick Britannia Award for Excellence
            in Film from the British Academy of Film and Television Arts (BAFTA).
            In 2014, he received a Kennedy Center Honor, and in 2016,
            he received a Presidential Medal of Freedom from President Barack Obama,
            as well as the French Legion of Honor.
        </biografija>
        <filmografija>Cast Away, Forrest Gump, Saving Private Ryan, Big, Sully, Catch Me If You Can</filmografija>
        <rezidencija>Los Angeles, California, U.S.</rezidencija>
    </glumac>


    <glumac glumacId="4" nacionalnost="AT" glumacSpol="M" wikiPageTitle="Arnold Schwarzenegger" brojDjece="5">
        <ime>Arnold</ime>
        <prezime>Schwarzenegger</prezime>
        <datum_rodjenja>July 30, 1947</datum_rodjenja>
        <partner statusVeze="Rastavljeni">
            <partnerIme>Maria</partnerIme>
            <partnerPrezime>Shriver</partnerPrezime>
        </partner>
        <zanimanje imeZanimanja="Glumac"/>
        <biografija>
            Arnold Alois Schwarzenegger is an Austrian-American actor, filmmaker, businessman, author,
            philanthropist, activist, politician, and former professional bodybuilder and powerlifter.
            He served as the 38th Governor of California from 2003 to 2011.
            Schwarzenegger began lifting weights at the age of 15.
            He won the Mr. Universe title at age 20 and went on to win the Mr. Olympia contest seven times,
            remaining a prominent presence in bodybuilding and writing many books and articles on the sport.
            The Arnold Sports Festival,
            considered the second most important professional bodybuilding event in recent years,
            is named after him.
            He is widely considered to be one of the greatest bodybuilders of all-time,
            as well as the sport's most charismatic ambassador.
            Schwarzenegger gained worldwide fame as a Hollywood action film icon.
            His breakthrough film was the sword-and-sorcery epic Conan the Barbarian in 1982,
            a box-office hit that resulted in a sequel.
            In 1984, he appeared in the title role of James Cameron's
            critically and commercially successful science-fiction thriller film The Terminator.
            He subsequently played a similar Terminator character in most of the franchise's later installments,
            Terminator 2: Judgment Day (1991), Terminator 3: Rise of the Machines (2003),
            and Terminator Genisys (2015).
            He has appeared in a number of other successful films, such as Commando (1985),
            The Running Man (1987), Predator (1987), Twins (1988), Total Recall (1990),
            Kindergarten Cop (1990), and True Lies (1994).
            Schwarzenegger married Maria Shriver,
            a niece of the 35th U.S. President John F. Kennedy and daughter of the 1972 Democratic vice presidential
            candidate and former Ambassador to France Sargent Shriver, in 1986.
            They separated in 2011 after he admitted to having fathered a child with another woman in 1997.
            As a Republican, Schwarzenegger was first elected on October 7, 2003,
            in a special recall election to replace then-Governor Gray Davis.
            He was sworn in on November 17, to serve the remainder of Davis' term.
            He was then re-elected in the 2006 California gubernatorial election,
            to serve a full term as governor.
            In 2011, he completed his second term as governor and returned to acting.
            Schwarzenegger was nicknamed "the Austrian Oak" in his bodybuilding days, "Arnie" or "Schwarzy"
            during his acting career, and
            "The Governator" (a portmanteau of "Governor" and "Terminator") during his political career.
        </biografija>
        <filmografija>
            Predator, Running Man, Terminator, Terminator 2: Judgement Day, Twins, Kindergarten Cop, True Lies
        </filmografija>
        <rezidencija>Los Angeles, California, U.S.</rezidencija>
    </glumac>

    <glumac glumacId="5" nacionalnost="GB" glumacSpol="M" wikiPageTitle="Ewan McGregor" brojDjece="4">
        <ime>Ewan</ime>
        <prezime>McGregor</prezime>
        <datum_rodjenja>31 March, 1971</datum_rodjenja>
        <partner statusVeze="Rastavljeni">
            <partnerIme>Eve</partnerIme>
            <partnerPrezime>Mavrakis</partnerPrezime>
        </partner>
        <zanimanje imeZanimanja="Glumac"/>
        <zanimanje imeZanimanja="Redatelj"/>
        <biografija>
            Ewan Gordon McGregor OBE is a Scottish actor and director,
            known internationally for his various film roles, including independent dramas,
            science-fiction epics, and musicals.
            McGregor's first professional role was in 1993,
            when he won a leading role in the British Channel 4 series Lipstick on Your Collar.
            Some of his best known roles include heroin addict Mark Renton in the drama films Trainspotting (1996)
            and T2 Trainspotting (2017), Jedi Obi-Wan Kenobi in the Star Wars prequel trilogy (1999–2005),
            poet Christian in the musical film Moulin Rouge! (2001), young Edward Bloom in Big Fish (2003),
            Rodney Copperbottom in Robots (2005),
            Camerlengo Father Patrick McKenna in Angels and Demons (2009),
            "the ghost" in Roman Polanski's political thriller The Ghost Writer (2010),
            Dr. Alfred Jones in the romantic comedy-drama Salmon Fishing in the Yemen (2011),
            Lumière in a live-action adaptation of the musical romantic fantasy Beauty and the Beast (2017),
            and the adult version of the titular character in the fantasy comedy-drama Christopher Robin (2018).
            In 2018, McGregor won a Golden Globe Award for
            Best Actor – Miniseries or Television Film for his performance as brothers in the third season of
            FX anthology series Fargo,
            and received Golden Globe nominations for Best Actor – Musical or Comedy for both Moulin Rouge!
            and Salmon Fishing in the Yemen. McGregor has also starred in theatre productions of Guys
            and Dolls (2005–07) and Othello (2007–08). He was ranked number 36
            on Empire magazine's "The Top 100 Movie Stars of All Time" list in 1997.
            In a 2004 poll for the BBC, McGregor was named the fourth most influential person in British culture.
            McGregor has been involved in charity work and has served as an ambassador for UNICEF UK since 2004.
            In 2013, he was appointed an Officer of the Order of the British Empire (OBE)
            for services to drama and charity. In 2016, he received the BAFTA Britannia Humanitarian Award.
        </biografija>
        <filmografija>
            Trainspotting, T2 Trainspotting, Star Wars Episode III: Revenge of the Sith, Beauty and the Beast
        </filmografija>
        <rezidencija>Los Angeles County, California, U.S.</rezidencija>
    </glumac>


    <glumac glumacId="6" nacionalnost="AT" glumacSpol="M" wikiPageTitle="Christoph Waltz" brojDjece="4">
        <ime>Christoph</ime>
        <prezime>Waltz</prezime>
        <datum_rodjenja>4 October, 1956</datum_rodjenja>
        <partner statusVeze="Oženjeni">
            <partnerIme>Judith</partnerIme>
            <partnerPrezime>Holste</partnerPrezime>
        </partner>
        <zanimanje imeZanimanja="Glumac"/>
        <biografija>
            Christoph Waltz; born 4 October 1956) is a
            German-Austrian film and voice actor and director mainly active in the United States.
            He is widely known for his work with American filmmaker Quentin Tarantino,
            receiving critical acclaim for portraying SS officer Hans Landa in Inglourious Basterds (2009)
            and bounty hunter King Schultz in Django Unchained (2012).
            For both performances, he earned an Academy Award, BAFTA Award,
            and Golden Globe Award for Best Supporting Actor.
            Waltz also received the Best Actor Award at the Cannes Film Festival
            and a Screen Actors Guild Award for his portrayal of Landa
            Waltz portrayed computer genius Qohen Leth in the science fiction film The Zero Theorem (2013),
            American plagiarist Walter Keane in the biographical film Big Eyes (2014),
            and James Bond's nemesis Ernst Stavro Blofeld in Spectre (2015),
            the twenty-fourth Bond film
        </biografija>
        <filmografija>
            Inglorious Basterds, Django Unchained, Zero Theorem
        </filmografija>
        <rezidencija>Berlin, Germany</rezidencija>
    </glumac>


</podaci>